And
Speaker 1: Mr. President, while we're on
Speaker 2: the
topic of
Speaker 2: actions taken by the Department of Defense that don't show
adequate
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and appropriate and necessary respect for those who stand in harm's way to protect us and defend us,
I want to
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): tell you the story
of
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): a brave
Speaker 5: young man, a U.S. Navy lieutenant named Ridge Alconis.
Mr.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): President, Ridge Alconis is one of the best and the brightest
that our Navy
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): has to offer, that America has to offer. A graduate of the U.S. Naval Academy,
a decorated
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): officer who served his country well,
who
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): goes above and beyond the call of duty by every account that I can find or that I have access to, Lieutenant Alconis, who is also the father of
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): three young children and the devoted husband to his wife, Brittany, sits today languishing in a
Japanese prison.
You may
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): ask, what has he done, what put him there?
Why is he in
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): prison in Japan?
Did he steal
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): something, did he harm
Speaker 7: someone? No,
none of the above. No, Mr.
Speaker 7: President, at
the end of May, May
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): 29th of 2021, Lieutenant Alconus and his wife,
Brittany,
along with
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): their three children, decided to take a brief road trip to go see Mount Fuji. And while descending from Mount Fuji,
he suffered a
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): most unfortunate, most unforeseen, and unforeseeable medical emergency, one that caused him to lose consciousness while driving.
His young
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): daughter, seeing that he had lost consciousness, tried to wake him
up.
She
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): kicked the seat, she yelled, she did everything she could to wake him up, and he didn't
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): wake up. You see, he wasn't asleep. He lost consciousness. He suffered from a rare medical condition that he didn't know
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): he had. He couldn't have known that he had this medical condition. It caused him to lose consciousness
at that moment.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Tragically, while
he was
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): unconscious, the car he was driving
I was
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): involved in an accident, one that took the lives of two Japanese nationals. My heart breaks for them, for the family members of these individuals whose lives were lost on May 29, 2021, in Japan.
I know that Lieutenant
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Halkonas, with whom I've spoken as I've visited him in prison in Japan,
His
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): heart breaks for them as well. Our entire country extends our thoughts, our prayers, and our well wishes to the family,
to the
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): family members of those victims.
But this was not a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): criminal act, Mr. President. This was a medical emergency, one that resulted in a tragedy. And I'm so sad that it did. And no one is more sad about this than Lieutenant Alconis and his family.
You see,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): in Japan,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): They have a different system than ours. In the United States, this wouldn't result in someone going to prison. This wouldn't result in criminal charges
of any kind.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): This would
be regarded
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): for what it is, which is a tragedy resulting from a medical emergency, an accident that wasn't foreseen or foreseeable. We wouldn't send someone to prison for that here in the United
States.
We
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): understand that different countries have different systems of law, and we do our very best to respect the laws of other countries, but that's why he's in prison today. My purpose in
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): raising this
today is to
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): talk about how our country handled it, not about how Japan handled it. We can talk about that perhaps on another day, but today I want
to talk
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): about how the United States military is handling this tragedy.
When a
Speaker 10: U.S. military
officer or
Speaker 10: enlisted person isn't
able to
Speaker 11: be present for duty,
he or she
Speaker 11: will stop
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): getting paid. Will stop getting paid if they're absent
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): their work. It's not surprising. Pretty much any job works that way and like most jobs,
if you're absent
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): from your work,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): your employer can make a decision about whether the absence was unavoidable and should therefore be
excused.
An
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): employer in the private sector might, for example,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): decide to continue to pay someone for a period of time if the circumstances warrant it. They might warrant it particularly
if the
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): absence was brought about
as a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): result of the conditions in which the person was
working on the
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): job. For example, imagine you were running a business and you had an employee.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): who you assigned to work somewhere in a foreign
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): country for a period of time. And something like this happened. I would imagine that many, if not most, if not all, sane employers would do everything they possibly could to take care of the family and
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): of that particular employee and that employee's
family.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): If something like this happened in a country
where
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): they were present only as a result of their work assignment. And in fact,
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): there is a statute that deals with this very thing for employees of the Department
of Defense.
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): That statute is codified at 37 U.S.C. Section 503. Here's what it says, Mr. President.
A
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): member of the Army, Navy, Air Force, Marine Corps, Space Force, Coast Guard, or National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration who is absent without
leave
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): or over leave forfeits all pay and allowances for the period of that absence unless it is excused
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): as unavoidable. Unless it is excused as unavoidable.
That's exactly what
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): the
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Department of Defense should do right now, Mr. President, is excuse, as unavoidable, Lieutenant Alconis'
absence. It seems to me
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): that if ever there were an instance perfectly
Speaker 19: tailored for this
Speaker 20: statute, if ever there were an absence that needed to be excused,
as
Speaker 20: unavoidable, it's that of Lieutenant Ridge Alconus.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): So with
that in
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): mind, and with
the needs
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): of his wife, Brittany, and their three young children who are
still in Japan,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Lieutenant Alconus
filed
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): the paperwork for an exception to policy with the Department of
Defense. Now, that
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): application was filed many, many
months ago, and we now find
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): ourselves in a situation in which that application has not been granted.
They
Speaker 20: filed this, I believe,
back in June.
Speaker 20: It was transferred from one office to another
in July.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): It was transferred, sent over to the office of the Under Secretary
of the
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Department of Defense a few months
later.
Speaker 22: It still hasn't been
acted on formally.
I've spoken
Speaker 23: with more officials within the Department of Defense
than I can even
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): count at this moment.
I've been
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): on this pattern of making phone calls since
just a few weeks
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): after this was filed in June. I've
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): spoken with officials within
the Department of Defense,
the
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): office of the Secretary of the Navy, including the Secretary himself, spoken to Undersecretary Cisneros, I've spoken even to Secretary of Defense Lloyd Austin, and I've appreciated their willingness
Speaker 9 (lower-pitched voice): to take my phone calls. And they still haven't acted. They still haven't granted
those.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Still hasn't happened.
Now keep
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): in mind,
This
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): has been in the office of the Secretary of Defense since September 3rd. So
we're going
Speaker 24: on
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): three and a half months since that was forwarded, and they still haven't acted. Now,
I finally spoke
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): with Undersecretary Cisneros. He was one of the last people I got through
Speaker 20: to. It took me three weeks to get through to the Undersecretary.
three
Speaker 11: weeks of calling
I finally
Speaker 11: got through to him and during that phone call it
appreciated the fact
Speaker 11: that he finally took it he assured
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): me that whatever decision was made it would be a decision that was made by the appropriate personnel and that
it would be in
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the best
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): whatever was in the best interests of the Department of Defense.
I told him at
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the time
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): I believed that what was best for the Alconus family would itself be what was in the best interests of the Department of Defense. You see, Mr. President, because there are a lot of
Speaker 19: problems that our Department of Defense has
right now.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Recruiting is down, morale is down, threats to our national security are up.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): There are more demands on our military men and women than ever before.
Why would you
Speaker 25: want to take one of your best and your brightest,
one of
Speaker 25: your smartest, one of these people who, I've talked to so many people who have worked with him
in his chain
Speaker 20: of command
who have
Speaker 20: described him as the kind of guy who will do something that needs to be done even before anyone else realizes it needs to be
done.
He'll go
Speaker 20: out on his own and proactively take steps to improve himself, to improve others around him. He's exactly what the Navy, what the Department of Defense, and what the United States of America
needs.
Speaker 25: So why? Why? When you put him in a vulnerable position, you send him
to Japan.
And
Speaker 25: look, I don't understand Japan's laws. They're very different than our own, but they're Japan. It's their country. Those are their laws. It's what
they do.
Speaker 26: We may not, within the United States government, be able to solve that particular issue. I
wish we
Speaker 26: could. I hope we can at some point. Those are conversations for a different day.
Speaker 27: But for today,
we can
Speaker 28: deal with this. We can take care
of this family.
Speaker 29: So,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): let's go back to November 2nd. So I had that conversation with Secretary Cisneros. I told Under
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): Secretary Cisneros that
it was
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): imperative that this be acted upon quickly because Rich Elkonis'
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): leave was going to be running out. You see,
since he
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): was actually put in prison in July of this year, it took, you know, between the accident that occurred
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): the end of May 2021, the time the criminal charges were filed and completed.
It wasn't until
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): July that he actually reported to prison. And since July, Lieutenant Alconis and his wife Brittany and their three children
Speaker 30: have been relying on the fact that he had accumulated leave, leave accumulated over the years,
that have
Speaker 30: lasted him
Speaker 31: this long.
And I told Under
Speaker 31: Secretary Cisneros on November 2nd,
It's
Speaker 31: really important that this be
Speaker 32: acted upon quickly because the Alconuses need this. They need this right away. They need the certainty of it. They need
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): to be
able to plan their
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): lives. I then started seeking a call with Secretary Austin, the Secretary of Defense. It took me three weeks to
get that
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): one scheduled. Three weeks. Finally spoke to him on
November 29th.
Secretary
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): Austin callously informed me that day
Speaker 33: that the request for the exception to policy would not be granted. I asked
him
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): why. He believed that it wasn't appropriate for the department to do that.
It was a
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): private conversation, so I'm not going to go into all the details
of it there.
But I
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): asked him at that moment,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): if that's your decision, will you at least formalize it
and put
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): it out so that it's in public, so that we can discuss it, so that its relative merits can be addressed, so that we as a
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Congress can figure out once on public notice of what the action was and why it was
taken?
how we
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): can decide how best to address it. If somehow, beyond my ability to comprehend as a lawyer and as a United States Senator, but if somehow the statutory text
of 37
Speaker 5: U.S.C. Section 503, if it contains something saying you may
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): not grant an exception to policy in this circumstance, similar to that of Lieutenant Alconis,
then
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): we could at least be on notice of that so that we as a Congress could figure
Speaker 34: out how to change the law so that it doesn't take that into account. I have yet to tell this story to a single member of the United States Congress, Democrat or Republican,
Speaker 20: House or Senate,
who isn't
Speaker 20: moved by this story and who doesn't conclude, well, of course, this is a no-brainer. Of course we should take care of him and his family. Of course they should be granted an
Speaker 34: exception to policy. But to do that, Mr. President, we have to be able to have the notice of what their decision
is,
the
Speaker 34: actual decision itself, and why it came
Speaker 5: about. I asked him when that would be coming, and he said, soon. And I said,
how soon?
Speaker 35: Reminding him that we're just weeks away. In fact, Mr. President,
we are
Speaker 20: now less than two weeks
away before
Speaker 20: Lieutenant Alconis' leave runs
out.
and before his
Speaker 20: wife, Brittany, and their three children, who are still in Japan, will have no source of income. These are three very young children.
The older
Speaker 20: kids are homeschooled by Brittany Alconis. They're in Japan, not a cheap place
to live,
Speaker 20: and their income stream is about
to run out.
Speaker 20: Now, the casual, calloused observer might respond by saying, "Okay, well then,
Speaker 20: then she can just go back to the United States.
Speaker 35: Okay, and then what? Go back to the United States. You know what that means? That would
mean that
Speaker 36: they don't ever get to see their husband and their
father. In
Speaker 36: fact, because of the way the rules work in Japan, they can't
Speaker 20: even talk to him
on the phone.
Speaker 20: There would be no interaction.
with
Speaker 20: Lieutenant Alconus by his wife and their three children if they just left. So leaving
is a
Speaker 20: problem. It still doesn't solve the problem of income. This very young, stay-at-home mom who homeschools their children. What is she supposed to do?
So she's got
Speaker 34: this Hobson's choice, this absolutely awful dilemma.
Rather than the
Speaker 34: prisoner's dilemma, we'll call it the prisoner's wife's dilemma.
Speaker 34: This is inexcusable the fact that they won't excuse as unavoidable Lieutenant Alconis's absence is itself inexcusable and we
Speaker 37: must act it's more difficult for us to act because the Department of Defense Hasn't even had the decency to issue a public pronouncement for this. I find this reprehensible
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Earlier today in fact just an hour or two ago I
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Mrs. Brittany Alconis
sent out a
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): series of tweets, and one of them
said the following.
Speaker 11: She said, "In 13 days, our pay and benefits "will be turned off. "I won't be able to support our children or RIDGE," that is, Lieutenant Alconis, "and I clearly won't be able to count on the U.S.
Navy
to do
Speaker 38: so either.
This is not a
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): way to treat those who stand
Speaker 39: in harm's way so that we can live and be safe and be free.
This isn't a way to
Speaker 39: treat anyone.
None of us
Speaker 40: would treat our employees that way. I don't know anyone who would.
On top of
Speaker 41: everything else,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): it's not just the fact that they've now stated that they're going to deny it, it's that they've waited so long to
do so.
and
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): that they still haven't had the decency to say so in public.
And then, on
Speaker 42: top of all of that,
they're going to have her
Speaker 42: kicked to
Speaker 43: the curb at
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Christmastime in
a foreign land. This is just
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): disgraceful. Look, I
get
Speaker 2: it.
I
Speaker 2: know the Department of Defense is really big. I know that
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the burdens faced by Secretary Austin, Under Secretary Cisneros, and so many others that I've
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): spoken to and those that I haven't spoken to within the Department of Defense, I know that they're immense. I'm grateful
to them
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): and for the service they provide to our great country. I'm grateful that they have taken
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): time to examine this
issue.
They've
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): reached the wrong conclusion, and they've done it in the wrong way.
Speaker 20: Fortunately, Mr. President, there's still time. The
time is short, but
Speaker 20: there's still time for them to make right that which is wrong.
They can still take care of
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): Brittany Alconis and the three children of Ridge and Brittany Alconis.
They can
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): still do that. I urge them to do
so.
If
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): they don't do it,
we will
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): have no choice as a Congress but to act. The Department of Defense may or may not like
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): whatever legislation we put in place in order to do it, but it'll happen. It's hard for it to happen, perhaps impossible for it to happen, until they issue their actual decision so that we know what
it is that we're
Speaker 45: correcting.
They
Speaker 45: should at least have the decency
to do that. But
Speaker 12 (lower-pitched voice): the United States must not allow this family to be treated this
way. In no
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): other circumstance that I can find has anyone going back many, many decades serving for
the
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): United States Armed Forces
in Japan
or any
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): other place that I'm
Speaker 20: aware of. Been placed in prison as a result of a medical emergency. So this truly is exceptional, and
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): that's what makes the exception to policy so meritorious and so worthy. He did nothing wrong, this was not foreseeable, it
Speaker 20: was not avoidable.
He was in
Speaker 20: Japan only because he was assigned to serve in Japan, where he has served faithfully.
We
Speaker 20: must correct this wrong, and I'll be back to the Senate floor as often as it takes.
Once we
Speaker 20: have the actual decision in hand, I'll know what legislation to push
for. I'll know what office
Speaker 46: to reconfigure, what statutory language to strip out or
add. They need to
Speaker 46: issue that right away, but even better,
They need
Speaker 4 (lower-pitched voice): to issue their decision not to deny, but to grant the exception to policy for Lieutenant Ridge Oconis.
The
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): Oconis family
and the
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): United States itself deserves nothing less. Thank you, Mr. President.